Since 2003, a special type of scam targeting the elderly
Od roku 2003 w Japonii króluje biorące na cel osoby starsze
called the money transfer scam has proliferated in Japan.
oszustwo zwane „przekrętem na przelew”.
Financial damages increased every year, reaching 56.5 billion yen in 2014.
Straty finansowe rosną z roku na rok. W 2014 r. wynosiły 56,5 miliarda jenów.
Now, in 2019, scammers have changed their techniques,
W 2019 roku oszuści zmienili metody,
and the damage continues.
w dalszym ciągu okradając obywateli.
Mom...
Mamo...
Is it that bad?
Jest aż tak źle?
One of the houses I work at was being robbed.
Okradali dom, w którym pracuję.
There were three of them,
Rabusiów było trzech.
and one of them asked the old man to come outside
Jeden z nich wywabił ofiarę,
while the others looked for money.
a pozostali przetrząsali dom.
That's when I arrived.
Wtedy weszłam.
They hit you?
Pobili cię?
I told them I didn't know where the money was.
Powiedziałam, że nie wiem, gdzie trzyma gotówkę.
Damn them.
Niech ich szlag.
This was a punishment.
To kara.
For?
Za co?
Punishment for scamming others.
Za oszukiwanie.
Don't be silly!
Nie wygłupiaj się.
If anyone were to be punished, it's me.
Jeśli ktoś zasługuje na karę, to ja.
I put that house on the register.
Ja podałam ten adres.
-Maybe one of your friends-- -That's impossible!
- Może twój znajomy... - Niemożliwe!
It's just a coincidence.
To zbieg okoliczności.
Come on!
Dalej!
Kazuto. Kazuto. Kazuto.
Kazuto.
EPISODE 7
ODCINEK 7
Let's try from this side now.
Teraz wejdź tędy.
Here we go!
Super!
Run, run!
Szybko!
You made it!
Udało ci się!
So? What's the emergency?
Co się pali?
Look at this.
Spójrz.
TODAY'S NEWS
WIADOMOŚCI
I saw this on the news.
Mówili o tym w wiadomościach.
A bunch of old people's homes were robbed, right?
Włamania do domów starszych osób.
Three in one week.
Trzy w jednym tygodniu.
All of these victims are on the M register.
To ofiary z rejestru M.
What?
Co?
-Someone's leaking information? -Maybe.
- Mamy przeciek? - Być może.
That's a huge problem!
To spory kłopot!
Where does the M register even come from?
Skąd wziąłeś ten rejestr?
I want you to tell me!
Mów!
-Don't tell anyone. -Of course not.
- Tylko nikomu nie mów. - Jasna sprawa.
My mom's a homecare worker, and she collected this data for me.
Moja mama jest opiekunką. Załatwiła mi te dane.
What?
Co?
She got caught up in a robbery and was badly injured.
Trafiła na włamanie i została pobita.
Do you think it's one of our guys?
Sądzisz, że to ktoś od nas?
Who leaked it?
Kto ujawnił informacje?
I don't want to doubt them, but...
Nie chcę w nikogo zwątpić, ale...
We'll stop using the M register.
Odstawimy ten rejestr.
If... And this is hypothetical,
To tylko hipoteza,
but if one of us leaked the info, who is it?
ale jeśli ktoś ujawnił rejestr, to kto?
It's not you, right?
Ty chyba nie?
Sorry, sorry.
Wybacz.
That leaves Gouriki...
Zostaje Gouriki...
Mori...
Mori...
And Kurusu.
I Kurusu.
Kusano, why did you get rid of the M register?
Dlaczego wycofałeś rejestr M?
We were doing so good.
Tak dobrze nam szło.
Just like you said, we shouldn't do anything to make Dokugawa-san angry.
Sam mówiłeś, żeby nie denerwować pana Dokugawy.
At this rate, we can hit our goal without it.
W tym tempie osiągniemy cel bez rejestru.
There's no reason to take risks.
Nie ma po co ryzykować.
And is the money collector problem taken care of?
Załatwili już kurierów?
Kanbe-san figured something out.
Pan Kanbe coś wymyślił.
Good to hear.
Świetnie.
I'm sorry for before.
Przepraszam za wtedy.
-How are your friends? -Friends?
- Co u twoich kumpli? - Kumpli?
The cavemen?
Jaskiniowców?
I said I'm sorry.
Przeprosiłem.
I haven't talked to them since.
Nie gadałem z nimi.
Let's go over again sometime
Trzeba znowu do nich wpaść
for some fresh seafood hot pot.
na świeże owoce morza.
The robberies stopped after we got rid of the M register.
Po wycofaniu rejestru skończyły się włamania.
I don't know if Kurusu was involved.
Nie wiem, czy to Kurusu.
We were on the brink of reaching our goal, and we couldn't afford any distractions.
Już prawie osiągnęliśmy cel, nic nie mogło nas rozpraszać.
"I'll make more money, then quit."
„Zarobię więcej i odejdę”.
That's what I promised my mom.
Obiecałem to mamie.
I'll go wash your cup.
Umyję ci kubek.
-Thank you.
- Dziękuję. - Dzięki.
The police officer came again.
Znów był tu ten policjant.
He said all the victims were our clients.
Ofiary były naszymi klientami.
He's getting suspicious.
Podejrzewa coś.
I don't think he suspects me yet, though.
Ale chyba nie mnie.
We won't get caught. Don't worry.
Nie złapią nas.
Are you sure? I'm scared.
Na pewno? Boję się.
Everything is fine.
Wszystko gra.
Okay.
Dobrze.
-Here. -Thanks.
- Trzymaj. - Dzięki.
Thanks for everything.
Dziękuję za pomoc.
It's okay.
Nie ma sprawy.
She probably prefers asking a woman's help for some things.
O niektóre rzeczy woli poprosić kobietę.
I know this is hard on you, too.
Wiem, że to dla ciebie ciężkie.
Visiting both your parents.
Odwiedzanie obojga rodziców.
Did you tell your dad?
Powiedziałeś tacie?
I told him that she got injured at work.
Tylko to, że miała mały wypadek w pracy.
I'll tell him the details once he's feeling better.
Powiem prawdę, gdy mu się polepszy.
I see.
Rozumiem.
It's just so terrible.
To okropne.
I almost started crying when I saw her injuries.
Prawie się rozpłakałam na jej widok.
What's wrong with those people?
Co jest z tymi ludźmi?
How could they do that?
Jak tak można?
This country has gone crazy.
Kraj oszalał.
The news is full of stories of children and the elderly being abused.
Wszędzie trąbią o przemocy wobec dzieci i starszych.
Was Japan always like this?
W Japonii zawsze tak było?
Was it like this when we were little?
Jak byliśmy mali?
It's terrible.
To okropne.
It's absolutely terrible.
Przerażające.
Here.
To tutaj.
-So, this is it? -Wait!
- Tutaj? - Moment!
Were we seen by anyone?
Ktoś nas widział?
Like who?
Kto?
If Dokugawa-san finds out, we're screwed.
Jak Dokugawa się dowie, mamy przesrane.
He's too busy for that.
Nie ma na to czasu.
-Come in. -Yeah.
- Chodź. - Jasne.
Don't mind the mess.
Wybacz bałagan.
-You okay with tap water? -Sure.
- Może być kranówka? - Jasne.
-Can I sit down?
- Mogę usiąść? - Pewnie.
Thanks.
Dzięki.
I took on a lot of debt back when I worked in the water business.
Zadłużyłem się w poprzedniej pracy.
I used to sell water coolers.
Sprzedawałem dystrybutory wody.
After that, I swore to never again buy water.
Obiecałem sobie, że już nigdy nie kupię wody.
Thanks.
Dzięki.
-I'll get the water. -Thanks.
- Naleję. - Dzięki.
-Here we go. -Do you want more?
- I już. - Jeszcze?
-Okay, a little. -A little.
- Troszkę. - Trochę.
Okay.
Dobra.
-Cheers.
- Zdrowie.
Tastes like tap water.
Smakuje jak kranówa.
Tap water is good.
Kranówa jest dobra.
This is rare for you, right?
To dla ciebie rzadkość, co?
-I only drink tap water. -Why?
- Piję tylko kranówkę. - Dlaczego?
Just buy fresh water.
Kupuj źródlaną.
-So, what's up? -Well...
- To co jest? - Cóż.
We're going to hit our goal soon.
Wkrótce osiągniemy cel.
Yep.
Tak.
If we succeed, then...
A wtedy...
I'm thinking of quitting.
chciałbym odejść.
Quit?
Odejść?
I know it's selfish.
Jestem egoistą, wiem.
But I promised my mom,
Ale obiecałem mamie,
-and I never planned to-- -Hold on.
- a nie planowałem... - Zaczekaj.
What'll happen to me?
A co ze mną?
We could quit together.
Możemy odejść razem.
Then we could look for a new job together or something.
Poszukać wspólnie pracy.
You're joking.
Żartujesz.
There's no jobs that'll accept both
Nigdzie nie przyjmą
a college graduate and middle school graduate.
kogoś po studiach i kogoś po liceum.
-If we look, maybe-- -There aren't any!
- Jak poszukamy... - Nigdzie!
Even if there were,
A nawet jeśli,
you'd abandon me in a second.
od razu byś mnie zostawił.
I get it.
Rozumiem.
You're okay with being my friend now,
Przyjaźnisz się ze mną
but that's just because of the job, right?
tylko ze względu na pracę?
Of course not!
Skądże!
So, now you're going to abandon me.
Chcesz mnie porzucić.
I really thought you and I would make it to the top.
Myślałem, że zajdziemy na szczyt.
Oh, well...
No nie.
-I'm just scared. -Of what?
- Boję się. - Czego?
Of getting caught?
Że nas złapią?
Of course.
No jasne.
-That'll hurt your perfect career. -It's not that.
- To ci zniszczy karierę. - Nie o to chodzi.
I've started to...
Ta praca...
enjoy this job.
zaczęła mi się podobać.
I'm scared of my own feelings.
Boję się swoich myśli.
Don't act like a smart-ass...
Nie zgrywaj cwaniaka...
after all this.
po tym wszystkim.
Okay.
Dobrze.
THE CON ARTISTS VOL. 14
KANCIARZE - CZĘŚĆ 14
I got it.
Mam.
Hey, stop it!
Przestań!
Hot!
Gorące!
You done?
Już?
We got the money!
Mamy forsę!
Money!
Szmal!
-Have some, Shiro. -What is this?
- Bierz, Shiro. - Co to?
It's corn soup.
Zupa kukurydziana.
-It's hot. -It is!
- Gorąca. - No.
What's wrong?
Co się stało?
We were robbed of nine million yen.
Ukradli nam dziewięć milionów.
What will you do about this?
Co z tym zrobisz?
Nothing.
Nic.
When we fail to collect, we just give up as if nothing happened. That's our rule.
Nieudane odbiory traktujemy z zasady tak, jakby nic się nie stało.
If we make it one man's fault,
Jeśli zrzucimy na kogoś winę
and he ends up going to the police, then we're all done for.
i ten ktoś pójdzie na policję, to po nas.
That's beautiful. Thank you for the lesson, Kanbe!
No pięknie. Wspaniała lekcja.
What about our injured man?
Co z pobitym kurierem?
We'll send him compensation. That's it.
Otrzyma wynagrodzenie. Wystarczy.
That's not it!
Nie wystarczy!
This guy is a reliable and seasoned professional.
To niezawodny, doświadczony zawodowiec.
And as soon as he does a job for you, he gets jumped?
Pracował dla ciebie i od razu go napadli?
Are you saying my men are involved?
Sugeruje pan, że to moi ludzie?
Yes.
Tak.
-Impossible. -Of course it's not!
- To niemożliwe. - Pewnie!
It's impossible.
To niemożliwe.
My men can make more money
Mogą zarobić więcej
by simply working hard.
ciężką pracą.
It's safer for them.
Tak jest bezpieczniej.
I see. Thank you for another great lesson.
Rozumiem. Kolejna wartościowa lekcja.
Quit patting yourself on the back and bring your men here, or I'll kill you!
Przestań się przechwalać i sprowadź ich tu, bo cię zabiję.
I trust them.
Ufam im.
Your store is being attacked.
Zaatakowano twój oddział.
Your money was stolen.
Ukradziono ci pieniądze.
Your own man was beaten up.
Pobito twojego człowieka.
What should you do?
Co zrobisz?
What's your job? You're the leader. Show some dignity!
Jesteś ich szefem. Miejże godność!
Bring me my nine million yen!
Przynieś mi moje dziewięć milionów!
Got it? Nine million by the weekend.
Masz czas do weekendu.
In this business, when things go wrong,
Czy w tej branży
shouldn't the financiers share the loss?
inwestorzy nie powinni pokryć części strat?
Nine million by the weekend.
Dziewięć baniek do weekendu.
And the fact that we were robbed as soon as we got a new collector
A skoro okradli nas, gdy wzięliśmy nowego kuriera,
shines the light of doubt on you!
to może być wasza sprawka!
Kanbe...
Kanbe.
do you really want to mess with me?
Naprawdę chcesz ze mną zadzierać?
Do you want a war?
Chcesz wojny?
A war would be bad.
Nie wygralibyśmy wojny.
But...
Ale...
You're right, Kanbe-san.
Ma pan rację.
If you went along with him, he'd get cocky and rob us again.
Gdybyście się dogadali, znów by nas okradł.
At any rate, things have fallen apart.
Tak czy siak, posypało się.
Nine million probably won't fix it.
Dziewięć milionów tego nie załatwi.
I'll give up whatever you need me to,
Oddam dla pana wszystko.
-whether it's money or a finger. -A finger?
- I forsę, i palec. - Palec?
-We're not the yakuza. -I'm serious.
- Nie jesteśmy yakuzą. - Naprawdę.
It's the leader's job to take responsibility when this happens.
Szef musi ponieść odpowiedzialność.
You know...
Wiesz...
I had the most fun when I was a player.
Lepiej bawiłem się jako zwykły gracz.
Working with you.
Pracując z tobą.
We went to the beach together.
Chadzaliśmy na plażę.
Yeah. We did.
To prawda.
The rules were less rigid then.
Nie było tak ciężko.
We drank, had barbeques together.
Razem piliśmy i jedliśmy.
And there was that guy who smashed a Jet Ski into a rock.
Pamiętasz gościa, który rozbił skuter wodny o kamień?
What was his name?
Jak on się nazywał?
It's best when it's extra crispy.
Najlepsze są chrupiące.
Right?
Prawda?
There's no doubt about it. None at all.
Niewątpliwie.
But you can't end there.
Ale to nie wszystko.
It's about the foundations.
Ważne są podstawy.
Why is it better crispy?
Dlaczego chrupiące?
In order to solve that, think back to your childhood.
Cofnijmy się do dzieciństwa.
Think about your foundations.
Pomyśl o swoich priorytetach.
When you were little, you'd scrape your knees and develop scabs, right?
Kiedyś ścierałeś sobie kolana i robiły ci się strupy.
Then you'd pull them off and eat them.
Odrywałeś je i jadłeś.
Do you get it?
Rozumiesz?
You get it, right?
Rozumiesz, prawda?
Crispy scabs.
Chrupiące strupki.
That's the reason people like crispy things.
Dlatego smakuje nam chrupiące jedzenie.
Things that are just a little wet.
Jedynie odrobinę wilgotne.
It's because they ate scabs.
Wszystko przez strupy.
That's why.
Właśnie.
Right?
Prawda?
Hello? Dokugawa-san?
Tak, panie Dokugawa?
Yes.
Oczywiście.
I'll take care of it.
Zajmę się tym.
Got it. Bye.
Rozumiem.
Sorry for the interruption.
Wybacz.
Scams are on the rise.
Coraz więcej oszustów.
You got that? Send the money right away!
Rozumiesz? Forsa, ale już!
Otherwise, I'll come to your house!
Bo do ciebie przyjdę!
Do you hear me?
Słyszysz?
We got it! Five million yen!
Tak! Pięć baniek!
-Yes! -Yeah!
- Tak! - Ekstra!
If we collect this, we'll reach our target!
Jak to odbierzemy, osiągniemy cel!
Wow.
Rany.
Incredible! Let's have a drink!
Niewiarygodne. Opijmy to!
I'll go get some beer.
Skoczę po piwko.
-Idiot, alcohol's not allowed. -We'll take shots of water.
- Nie wolno nam pić, durniu. - Wzniesiemy toast wodą.
You're killing me!
No nie.
Dokugawa-san? It's me, Kusano.
Panie Dokugawa? Mówi Kusano.
Please send someone to take five million from our sixth account.
Proszę wysłać kogoś po pięć milionów od celu numer sześć.
Yes.
Tak.
No way.
Nie do wiary.
Just do it.
Dawaj.
-What? -Let's go out after this.
- Co? - Wyskoczmy gdzieś.
-It should be fine, right? -I think so.
- Będzie dobrze? - Chyba tak.
I told you not to call my work phone!
Dlaczego dzwonisz na służbowy?
If something happens, I'll call you.
Zadzwonię, jak coś się stanie.
Yeah.
Tak.
I'll check later.
Sprawdzę to.
You should only use that for work.
To telefon tylko do pracy.
Whatever you say.
Jasne.
Hey, Seimiya.
Seimiya.
-I... -You're leaving soon, huh?
- Ja... - Odchodzisz?
Congratulations.
Gratuluję.
Give us the money.
Dawaj forsę.
Hand over the money!
Oddawaj forsę!
Money! Money!
Szmal!
All this money!
Ile siana!
Yay!
Rany!
Money!
Szmal!
What? This isn't money!
Że co? To nie forsa!
What the hell is this?
Co to ma być?
What?
Co?
You shouldn't have--
Popełniłeś błąd...
Let's go!
W nogi!
Shiro!
Shiro!
To the elderly disease!
Na pohybel staruchom!
Cheers!
Zdrowie!
We did it!
Udało się!
Come visit my hometown.
Wpadnijcie do mojego miasta.
That'll be fun!
Będzie super.
It'll be fun.
Będzie.
-Okay. -I know some good places.
- Jasne. - Znam fajne knajpy.
But let's keep this a...
Ale nie róbmy z tego...
Wait!
Stój!
Go get him! Now!
Brać go! Już!
-What did Kurusu do? -That punk
- Co on zrobił? - Ten śmieć
was working with the robbers!
współpracował ze złodziejami!
Go after him! You stay here! Hurry!
Za nim! A ty tu zostań! Już!
Give me a freakin' break!
Dajcie spokój!
We gotta leave now!
Spadamy!
Get all of the money together!
Bierzcie forsę!
Hurry!
Szybko!
What happened to Shiro?
Co z Shirem?
I don't give a damn about him!
Mam go w dupie!
They'll get us in no time! Hurry!
Zaraz nas dorwą!